# 大家好 很久都沒來這個新廠房啦 你看
Hi everyone! I haven't been to this new site for a pretty long time. Look!
# 現在都
Now,
# 到處都是那個 雜草從生
the weed is, the weed is growing everything.
# 而且這門口上有一個那麼大的黃蜂窩
And there's also such a big nest of wasps in front of the door.
# 今天要進 進裡面 你看這個黃蜂擋住了路
We're gonna get, get inside today. Look! The wasps are blocking our way.
# 要把它捅下來喲
I gotta poke it down.
# 你看 那些黃蜂 它們都好激動啊
Have a look at those wasps! They're so excited.
# 一直都在那盤旋
They keep circling around over there,
# 看著我
staring at me.
# 等一下 我來 等下我來接 讓它們 讓他們的
A moment. I'm gonna, I'll tackle them in a while. Let them, let their,
# 情緒先恢復一下
their emotion cool down a bit first.
# 你看 到處都是 東飛西飛的
Look! They're everywhere, flying here and there.
# 好多子啊 到這邊來
There are a lot of larvae and pupae. Let's go to this side.
# 你看 這裡飛出 飛來一個
Look! A wasp is flying, flying from here.
# 幸好它沒看到我
Fortunately, it can't see me.
# 太嚇人啦
It's scary!
# 突然之間跑過來的哦
It popped up all of a sudden, you know.
# 不是我 不是我把你的窩捅下來的
It was not me. I didn't poke your nest down.
# 是那個棍子 別找我哦
It was that rod. So leave me alone!
# 你看 這些蜂蛹 你看
Look! These are the pupae, look!
# 都還有好多
There are still a lot.
# 這可以直接吃的哦
These can be eaten right away, you know.
# 問你敢不敢吃
The problem is whether you dare or not.
# 我是還小的時候吃了好多
I did eat a lot when I was small.
# 就是
It's like,
# 優質的蛋白質來源
a source of high quality protein.
# 你看 這個蜂蛹 看 就這種
Look! This is a pupa. It looks like this.
# 很好吃的
It tastes really good.
# 不能咬哦 一咬就
Make sure that you don't chew it. If you do,
# 就那個
it would be, you know...
# 多吃幾個 可以哦 這個味道
Let me eat a few more. It's really not bad, the taste.
# 哎 出來 你看 就那麼
Ay! Get out! Look! Here it is.
# 就這樣的 這個還會動的 看到沒有
Here it is. It's, it's still moving. See?
# 這個要活吃哦 如果 你把它咬碎了就
It needs to be eaten alive. If you chew it, it would be,
# 太那個啦 是啊 就這樣直接吞掉就好啦
too, you know.. Yea, just swallow it right away.
# 不知道你們還小的時候有沒吃過
Have you ever eaten these things when you were small?
# 我還小吃了好多這樣的
I used to eat a lot when I was small,
# 黃蜂子
I mean wasps larvae and pupae.
# 這一個
This one...
# 這種用油炸一下也可以吃的哦 這個
They can also be fried in oil, these things.
# 你看 這裡也有
Look! Some more here
# 來 吃一個
C'mon! Take one!
# 誒 掉啦
Ey? It dropped.
# 這樣 等一下不要啦
Well, doesn't matter.
# 等叫那鴨子過來把它吃掉
I'll let the duck eat it in a while.
# 嗯 要不要吃一個
Um! You want one?
# 嘗一個
Try one!
# 看你口水都流出來啦
I see that you're already drooling.
# 上次我們吃的是那個
What we ate last time were the,
# 我們這邊叫
here we call them,
# 辣椒蜂 就是那個蟄一下那個 手很辣的
"chilli wasps". It's like its sting burns, burns the hand.
# 這種不一樣 這種是稍微比較大的 這個是真正的
But this one is different. These are larger. They're the authentic,
# 那個黃蜂來的 這大黃蜂
authentic wasps. These are big wasps.
# 這還有 幾個
Here are still, a few.
# 以前 蛋白質來源 以前家裡沒有肉吃
It was, a source or protein. We hardly had any meat at home in the past.
# 吃點 這個蛋白質
We ate this. Its protein,
# 它這挺好的
is in fact quite good.
# 還有幾個給那個小鴨子吃
The last few are left for the duckies.
# 你看 買了七八十隻鴨子回來
Look! I've bought around eighties ducks back here.
# 現在這個廠房一直都空著看 現在買了一些鴨子回來
This site has always been idled. So I've bought some ducks.
# 買了七八十隻鴨子放在這裡
I've bought seventy or eighty ducks and leave them here.
# 這個 呃 窗戶在外面啊 就是有幾個大魚塘
It's, eh, outside the windows, there's a couple of big ponds.
# 剛好它們
Right now they're here.
# 有空閒的時候就可以把它們趕到池塘裡面去
I can drive them to the ponds when I'm free.
# 看這有好吃的
I have something tasty here.
# 蟲子哦
Bugs!
# 蛋白質 營養豐富
Rich in protein, and nutritious
# 你們可能沒吃過
I bet it's your first time.
# 你看 嘗到味道啦 它們在搶
Look! Once they've tasted it, they're now fighting over it.
# 你看 這還有一個
Look! One more is here.
# 這鴨子還小的時候好可愛的哦 你看 那麼小就游泳
These ducks are really lovely when they're small. Look! Though they're so small, they can swim already.
# 長大了 就很好吃
And they'll be really tasty when they grow up.
# 至少養個四五個月
They need to be raised for about four or five months.
# 養 養不夠四五個月長不大 因為這個可能
Any, anything less than four or five months doesn't work at all. I think it's because,
# 到後面直接玉米給它吃
they're given corns right away at later stages.
# 不給飼料給它吃
No fodder is given.
# 週期長一點 但是 肉質還是可以的
The period becomes longer. But, the texture of the meat is not bad.
# 這個是土鴨子 長不了多大的 這個
These ducks are native here. They, they don't get really big.
# 你看 這裡還有一個黑色的鴨子 小黑 小黑鴨
Look! Here's a black duck, a little black, little black ducky.
# 看到沒有 在那裡 我都沒發現 抓的時候
See? It's over there. I didn't notice it when I was picking them.
# 讓它們慢慢慢慢的就習慣這裡啦
Little by little, they'll get used to this place.
# 在這裡放回去 它們自己會回家
Then I can release them. They''ll know their way home.
# 這裡好多草啊 到處都是
Here's a lot of grass. It's everywhere.
# 哎呀 這樣都沒抓到你
Aya! How can you escape from me?
# 你看 這吃的好飽啊 看到沒 這都鼓起來啦
Look! It has eaten a lot! See? It's popping out here.
# 那麼小
It's so small.
# 你看 它口水都流出來啦 看到沒有
Look! It's drooling. See?
# 我也流出來啦
And I'm drooling too.
# 你還小 好可愛啊 還小的時候
You're still small. It's so lovely, when it's small.
# 誒喲 既然吐口水給我
Ayo! It spits on me!
# 那麼壞你
You're so naughty!
# 放了你
I let you go.
# 都一群一群的 它不會單獨分開的
They're always in a herd. There's no lone duck.
# 養大啦 好大啦 是個 整個都是滿的
When they grow up, they'll b really big. Yea, they'll occupy the whole room here.
# 每天餵一點給它吃就可以啦 不用餵那麼多的
A little bit of food every day is enough, not too much.
# 它也跑不了
They can't run away anyway.
# 一下子餵多一點啊 讓它們夠吃一天的量就可以啦
A little bit more at a time, enough for a whole day, is everything needed.
# 好啦 現在回去啦
Alright! We're going back now.